<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Maries in Oxford, the 17. day of November, 1602. in defence of the festivities of the Church of England, and namely that of her Maiesties coronation. By Iohn Hovvson Doctor of Divinitie, one of her Highnes chaplaines, and vicechancellour of the Vniversitie of Oxforde</title>
            <author>Howson, John, 1557?-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119077</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854284</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854284</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19695</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19695)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1072:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Maries in Oxford, the 17. day of November, 1602. in defence of the festivities of the Church of England, and namely that of her Maiesties coronation. By Iohn Hovvson Doctor of Divinitie, one of her Highnes chaplaines, and vicechancellour of the Vniversitie of Oxforde</title>
                  <author>Howson, John, 1557?-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Barnes, and are to be sold in [London in ] Fleete-streete at the signe of the Turkes head by Iohn Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>For another defence of accession day celebrations see STC 13596.5--STC.</note>
                  <note>Place of distribution from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi²  A-D⁴ (-D4, blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Sion College. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19695:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. MARIES IN OXFORD, THE 17. DAY OF NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember, 1602. in defence of <hi>the Festivities of the Church of England, and namely that of her Maieſties Coronation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>IOHN HOVVSON DOCTOR OF Divinitie, one of her Highnes Chaplaines, and Vicechancellour of the Vniverſitie of Oxforde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Joſeph Barnes, and are to be ſold in Fleet-ſtreete at the ſigne of the Turkes head <hi>by Iohn Barnes.</hi> 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19695:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19695:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, my very eſpecial good Lord, THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS <hi>Baron of Buckhurſt, Lorde high</hi> Treaſurer of England, one of the LL. <hi>of her Maieſties moſt honorable Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie Councell, Knight of the honorable</hi> Order of the Garter, and Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of the Vniverſitie <hi>Of Oxford.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, the day now vſually ſolemnized to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and memory of thoſe bleſsings wherewith hee hath enriched this land in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and his Church in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, by the godly and religious government of her excellent Maieſtie, was with the firſt cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated (as we take it,) in this her moſt loyall and Chriſtian Vniverſitie of Oxford, notwithout the example of former times, wherein the like hath beene practiſed to ſome of her Maieſties prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, though with different ceremonie in a different religion. Since which time it having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken progreſſe togither with Gods manifold bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, &amp; enlargement both in place and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, teſtifying the loyall harts, and duetifull lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:19695:3"/>
affection of her ſubiects, both to her royall perſon, ſincere religion, and moſt bleſſed go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as alſo their harty thankefulnes vnto God for them: it hath beene oppugned by the Preiſtes &amp; Ieſuites, the enemies of her gracious peace and happie proſperitie, whether with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter malice or ignorance I cannot well determine. VVherefore being called to the celebration of this moſt happy feſtiuity, by the nature of my office, which by your Lordſhips appointment (though vnworthily) I ſuſteine: I thought it a part both of my duety to God, and loyalty to my ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Miſtres, to vndergoe the defence of the feſtivities of our Church, which haue their adverſaries at home among vs, as of the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the day of her moſt bleſſed inauguration into this kingdome, which hath found ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligners both at home and abroad, &amp; to dedicate the ſame to your Honor, as my chiefeſt Patrone vnder her Highnes, not preſuming to preſent her ſacred Maieſtie with ſo meane and ſimple a ſervice, &amp; ſo in al humility I take my leave. From Chriſt-church. Novem. 29. An. Dom. 1602.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors in all ſervice,</hi> IOHN HOVVSON <hi>Vicecan. Oxon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19695:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>This is the day which the Lord hath made, we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice and be glad in it. <hi>PSAL. 118.24.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pſalme is a Pſalme of thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, which <hi>David</hi> ſong vnto God, when hee was firſt inveſted into his kingdome,<note place="margin">2. King. 6.</note> and tranſlated the Arke of the Lord from the houſe of <hi>Obed Edom,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 6. with melody and muſicke and greate feſtivitie; in which he not only exhorteth <hi>all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> in a generalitie to praiſe God, &amp; in ſpecialitie both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſuch as were after the ſpirit borne of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and deteſted Idolatrie as <hi>Abraham</hi> did: but actually bringeth in himſelfe, <hi>ver.</hi> 17.<note place="margin">ver 17. ver. 24. ver. 26.</note> the people in this verſe, and the Prieſts in the 26. verſe, glorifying God for theſe great bleſſings.</p>
            <p>The king both privately alone, and publikely in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, prepareth himſelfe to this thankſgiving, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging Gods iuſtice in humbling him, his mercy in preſerving him in the daies of <hi>Saule</hi> who ſought his life, and his bounty in inveſting him into his kingdom, ſaying, <hi>ver.</hi> 22.<note place="margin">ver. 22.</note> 
               <hi>The ſtone which the builders refuſed is now become the head stone in the corner.</hi> I who was reiected by <hi>Saule</hi> and his princes, am now inaugurated into the kingdome. Which though it be here an hiſtorical confeſſion,<note place="margin">Mat. 5. Act. 2.1. Pet. 2.</note> is not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding a prophetical revelation of the kingdome of
<pb facs="tcp:19695:4"/>
Chriſt. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>The people provoked by their kings example anſwere him,<note place="margin">ver. 23.</note> 
               <hi>This is the Lords doing and it is wonderfull in our eies.</hi> And exhort one another to the celebration of that day in which God had wroughte that wonder in inveſting and crowning him, againſt whom ſo many, ſo great men ſo long time had conſpired: ſaying: <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made, wee will reioice and be glad in it;</hi> and then doe pray for the continuance and long life of their prince and his proſperity, <hi>O domine da ſalutem, ô domine da proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritatem.</hi> O Lord giue health, giue ſalvation, O Lord giue proſperitie vnto our king.</p>
            <p>Finally the Prieſts ſeeing this harmonie and conſent in the people,<note place="margin">ver. 26.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſe them for it, wiſh them good lucke,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that great light and bleſſing to be given of God, and exhorte them to that publike ceremoniall ſervice of God which was vſed in thoſe times.<note place="margin">ver. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Binde your ſacrifices with cordes even to the hornes of the altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words which I haue read vnto you for my text, haue bin heretofore applied by the fathers of the church, ſometimes to the celebration of the Nativity, ſometimes to the celebration of the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt; as wel they may be, this Pſalme being figuratiuely and ſpiritually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to him, as appeareth by manie places of ſcripture: but I am to take it this day litterally of the inthroniſing of <hi>David,</hi> being the day conſecrated to the glory of God for the inauguration of our bleſſed Soveraigne into this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. In which words I obſerue the inſtitution of a feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val day, and therein, <hi>Firſt</hi> the occaſion of the Inſtitution, which are Gods bleſſings extraordinary, cowched vnder theſe words: This is the day which the Lord hath made. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the author of the Inſtitution: king <hi>David. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19695:4"/>
the End or vſe of it; wherin I note an external ioy, <hi>Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temus,</hi> Let vs reioice: and an internal, <hi>Laetemur in ea,</hi> let vs be glad in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt for the Inſtitution and occaſion of it.<note place="margin">1. Part. Inſtitution.</note> It is certaine that al daies were firſt made and created by God; hee made the firſt day, and the ſecond, and the third &amp; the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, and placed in the firmament a great light, namelie the ſunne, which by his preſence or abſence without al re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect diſtinguiſheth daies from nights, and one day from another. Nevertheleſſe though God be the auctor of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al, yet hee hath put a difference and diſtinction betweene them, and is ſaid more eſpecially to haue made one then another: more eſpecially the Sabboth and holy-day, then the ordinary day appointed for labour: <hi>Propter opera pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilegiat a quae fecit in eis,</hi> for certaine excellent and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged workes which he hath done in it.</p>
            <p>And this is noted by the wiſe ſonne of Sirach Cap. 33. Who graunting a diſtinction of daies, but demaunding a reaſon of it, putteth this queſtion.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 33.</note> 
               <hi>VVhy doth one day excell another ſeeing the light of the daies of the yeare</hi> (that is the life of them) <hi>comes of the ſunne.</hi> &amp; he maketh this anſwer: The knowledge of the Lord hath parted them a ſunder, &amp; he hath diſpoſed by them the times &amp; the ſolemne feaſts: ſome of them he hath put among the daies to number, &amp; ſome of them hath he choſen &amp; ſanctified, &amp; exalted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to feaſtes: that is, ſome are feſtival as the Paſſeouer, Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt, feaſt of Tabernacles &amp;c. and ſome are numerall, the firſt or ſecond of this or that moneth.</p>
            <p>For God hath dealt with daies as with men: for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are al of the ground, and Adam was created out of the earth, but the Lord hath diſtinguiſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by great knowledge, &amp; made their waies &amp; reputations diverſe: ſome of them
<pb facs="tcp:19695:5"/>
hath he bleſſed and exalted, as kinges and princes: &amp; ſome of them he hath ſanctified, and appropriated to himſelfe, as Prophets and Prieſtes: but ſome hee hath curſed and brought lowe, and put them in meane eſtate, and place of baſe calling.</p>
            <p>Now the meanes which God vſeth in advancing ſome daies before their fellowes, which are made of the ſame mettal and ſubſtance with them, is ſome excellent worke, ſome admirable bleſſing performed in them, ſometimes generally to al mankind, ſometimes ſpecially to theſe or theſe nations. And according to the generality or ſpeciali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is the quantity of them: and according to the nature &amp; conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the bleſſing or benefite, is the quality of them. For ſome are ſuch, <hi>Quae tota per vniver ſum orbe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frequentas eccleſia,</hi> which the whole church throughout the whole world doth frequent: ſome are vſed in this country, in that kingdome. Some are <hi>festiuitates magnae,</hi> high feſtival daies: and ſome are called the lower feaſtes.</p>
            <p>That general &amp; admirable benefit which was done to al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind by the creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man, &amp; the whole world for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſake, is offered perpetually to the memory of al mankind by the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Sabboth, which although the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then in truth ſcorned,<note place="margin">Iuvenal Sa. 14.</note> as appeareth, Iuuenal: Sat. 14. <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſortiti metuentem Sabbata patrem &amp;c.</hi> yet the whole world ought now, and no doubt in the beginning even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Moſes law did obſerue it, being a part of the decalog, and conſequenly in ſome ſort of the law of nature it ſelfe. And therefore that of Iob 3.4.<note place="margin">Iob. 3.4. Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>Dies ille vertatur intene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras, non requirat eam Deus de ſuper,</hi> St. Chryſoſtome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreteth. Let not God make an holy-day of it. <hi>Non diem illam tanquam ſuam vendicet dominus,</hi> let not the Lord ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it as his day; &amp; learned interpreters vpon that place
<pb facs="tcp:19695:5"/>
obſerve, <hi>Antiquos patres in lege naturae, forte etiam Iobum, Sabbatizaſſe:</hi> That the auncient fathers vnder the Law of nature and peradventure Iob himſelfe, obſerved the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both.</p>
            <p>That general and admirable benefite of our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which was ſufficient for the whole world, but efficient to al the elect of God, as it ought ſo it hath beene time out of mind celebrated in the feaſts of the Conception, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion, Paſſion, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion of Chriſt by the whole Church of God, diſperſed farre and neere over the face of the earth, to the honor of God with praiers and thankeſgiving for the ſpecial benefits particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly called to minde and acknowledged vppon thoſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne daies. Wherefore Eraſmus did not onely abſurdly,<note place="margin">Eraſmus.</note> when he vilified thoſe feaſts, and falſely when he ſaid <hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus veterum facit vllam festi mentionem,</hi> No ancient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter maketh mention of any feaſt, though cunningly he ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it with <hi>Quantum memini</hi> As far as I remember; but he did amiſſe alſo in aſſigning the reaſon of the Inſtitution of our Sunday or Dominical day, ſaying, <hi>Diem dominicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babili cauſa maiores noſtros feſtum eſſe voluiſse, vt populus conveniret ad audiendum ſermonem Evangelij</hi> That our forefathers were willing to haue the Lords day a feaſt for a probable or reaſonable cauſe, that the people might aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble togither to heare the word of the goſpel preached. For that is not the onely end, or chiefe end of the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords day, much leſſe of other feaſtes, ſeeing God is not onely or chiefely worſhipped <hi>Evangelici ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monis auditu,</hi> by hearing the word preached, <hi>ſed latria cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu,</hi> in praiſing, and magnifying, &amp; lauding God in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of his manifold bleſſings. Seeing <hi>latria</hi> or the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe of God conſiſteth eſpecially in praying and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving,
<pb facs="tcp:19695:6"/>
and is a vertue morall, &amp; not intellectual. Therfore to deſpiſe, (as manie do,) or neglect (as moſt do) <hi>cultum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria,</hi> and gad vp &amp; downe to heare the word preached, as they cal it, is not onely againſt the lawes of this land, the ſtatutes of our colledges, but againſt the chiefe Inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lords day.</p>
            <p>Yet wel-fare the wiſedome and diſcretion of our great grandfathers of bleſſed memory, the ſaints of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church, who provided that vpon the feſtival daies, the courſe of the Litargie, the Goſpell, and Epiſtle, the Homile, or Sermon ſhoulde ſo bee ordered, that all ſhoulde rende to the memorie of that bleſſing, wherevnto that day was ſanctified, that ſo God might bee bleſſed and magnified for them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iuvenal.</note>Beloued Chriſtians were any one of thoſe excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers aliue, what thinke you would he ſaie, <hi>Quid diceret, aut quid non faceret,</hi> nay what would he not do, if he ſhould ſee the Synagogues of the Iews where Moſes was read, more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the three ſolemne feaſts of <hi>Easter, Pentecoſt,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> then the temple of Ieruſalem whither by the law al ought at thoſe times to reſorte to offer vp ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vnto God: If he ſhould ſee <hi>Oratoria</hi> turned into <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditoria,</hi> Churches into Schooles, our people deſiring ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> knowers, then <hi>Seraphim,</hi> hot &amp; zealous, crying with the Angels, <hi>holy, holy, holy,</hi> Lord God of hoaſts: our Sabbothes and Feſtivities not ſpent nor anie part of them, in <hi>cultu latriae,</hi> in the divine ſeruice of God, but in hearing an exerciſe as ſome call it; where ſometimes the houre is conſumed, <hi>Nihil dicendo</hi> in ſpeaking neuer a wiſe word, ſometimes <hi>aliud dicendo</hi> in ſpeaking from the daie, from the ſeaſon, from the text, and ſometimes <hi>Male dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> in ſpeaking ill, and ſlaundring their private governours or publike magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19695:6"/>But I proceed. Not only the forenamed feaſts &amp; ſuch like which are called by the Divines, <hi>Solennes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Solennes.</note> are inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſervice of God, and occaſioned by ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary bleſſing: but other feaſts there are, which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by <hi>Macrobius, Satur.</hi> 1. <hi>ca</hi> 16. <hi>Imperativae:</hi> by <hi>Vlpian</hi> and other Civilians <hi>Extraordinariae:</hi> by certaine Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts <hi>Repentinae,</hi> which are particular to divers nations,<note place="margin">Vlpian.</note> &amp; celebrated to the memoriall of Gods particular bleſſings beſtowed on them. Such are they wherein great Kings &amp; Monarches haue either <hi>Lucis auſpicia</hi> (as the Civilians cal them) the daie of their birth; or <hi>Ortus imperij</hi> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Raigne. The one is the ſolemnization of their Nativity: the other, the inauguration into their kingdom: ſuch a one is this here mentioned in my text, inſtituted to the honor of God, for the great bleſſing that befel the Iews when <hi>David</hi> firſt tooke poſſeſſion of the kingdome: and ſuch a one is this wee celebrate this day throughout our land, to giue thankes to God for the happy raigne of our Soveraigne Princeſſe.</p>
            <p>Finally, we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude of al Chriſtian feaſts whether general to the whole Church, or particular to any nation, as <hi>Abulenſis</hi> doth of the feaſtes of the Iewes, <hi>Omnia festa quae Deus instituit obſervanda à Iudaeis, fiebant ad recorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem beneficiorum eius,</hi> All feaſts which God appointed the Iewes to obſerue were kept for a remembrance of his benefits, except only the feaſt of Propitiation, <hi>Quod fiebat ad remiſsionem peccatorum,</hi> which was helde for remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>But heere ariſeth a doubt, whether Kings and Princes now, or <hi>David</hi> himſelfe heretofore did wel and religiouſly to honor and glorifie God for this bleſſing of his inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or anie temporal happines, ſeeing we muſt loue &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:19695:7"/>
honor God <hi>Propter ſeipſum, &amp; quia ſummè bonus eſt,</hi> for himſelfe and becauſe he is chiefly good, and not eſpecially for thoſe benefits he giveth vnto vs.</p>
            <p>For every temporall benefite is leſſe then infinite, but his goodneſſe is infinite, therefore his goodnes ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe vs to loue and honour him, then his benefites: therefore though poore ſimple people may honour God for his benefites receiued, and in hope to receiue more, yet <hi>David</hi> being a Saint and a Prophet, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, ſhould haue honored God <hi>propter Deum,</hi> becauſe he was God, and not becauſe hee poſſeſt him of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>The aunſwere in this ſcarſitie of time muſt bee briefe: wherfore I ſay that a man is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to loue &amp; honor God in that degree in which he honoreth him, that is, <hi>cultu latriae</hi> with divine worſhip, becauſe he is his God not becauſe he is his benefactour: wherfore if it were poſſible, as it is not, that any man or other creature could beſtow all theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits that God hath vouchſafed vs, yet wee ought not to honor him with divine worſhip with which we honor God nay ſo to do were impious Idolatrie: Againe if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as it is not, that God neuer had, nor euer could bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite or bleſſe vs, yet we were bound to honor him <hi>cultu la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria</hi> with divine worſhip: and there is no doubt <hi>David</hi> &amp; other princes honoured God <hi>cultu latria</hi> with divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe <hi>ſolum quia Deus eſt, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propter beneficia accepta,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe he is God, not for the benefites they haue from him.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this <hi>latria</hi> divine worſhippe is not <hi>totalitèr determinata</hi> namely to theſe or thoſe ceremonies to theſe or thoſe times: and men in this worlde cannot beſtowe al times vpon it, therefore <hi>cultus latria</hi> the divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb facs="tcp:19695:7"/>
or honor is done vnto God, <hi>Quia Deus</hi> eſt, becauſe he is God: but vpon this day or that day, &amp; in this or that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Quia benefactor,</hi> becauſe he is our benefactour. And thus much of the Occaſion of the Inſtitution of this feaſt, namely ſome extraordinary bleſſing, noted in theſe words <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I obſerue in the Inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this feaſt or holydaie.<note place="margin">2. part.</note> 
               <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made;</hi> which we are not to vnderſtand as though God himſelfe had inſtituted this feſtivitie; for theſe words note not the Author, but the occaſion of the Inſtitution:<note place="margin">Hugo Card.</note> the Lorde who makes al daies is ſaide to make this <hi>ſpecialiter, propter privilegiata opera qua fecit in ea; Huge Card.</hi> ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, for the priviledged workes which he did in that day,<note place="margin">Gloſſa in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlin. Lyra.</note> 
               <hi>Propter ſalutem quam dedit populo &amp; principi: Gloſsa inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin:</hi> for the ſafetie he gaue to prince and people: <hi>Propter bonum quod in illa contigit: Lyra.</hi> For the good which befel that daie: but the Author of this inſtitution was <hi>David</hi> himſelfe. God gaue the occaſion, <hi>David</hi> the inſtitution.</p>
            <p>But becauſe there is a queſtion made eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe daies, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the authority of inſtituting holydaies both vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the olde and newe Teſtament, both among Iewes and Chriſtians, ſome affirming that in the old law all were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by God himſelfe, or by his commaundement by Moſes, and that to the Moſaical law nothing might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no not in ceremonies; and foraſmuch as the old feaſts were abrogated by Chriſt, and no other inſtituted by him or his Apoſtles, except peradventure the Lords day, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore al are vnlawful for want of authoritie in the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or inſtitutors of them: may it pleaſe you to giue mee leaue to deliver vnto you, of neceſſitie verie briefly, who haue beene the Authors of feaſts and holydaies in both
<pb facs="tcp:19695:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thoſe times, to both thoſe people.</p>
            <p>Firſt by the commaundement of God himſelfe by the mouth of Moſes were inſtituted in the old law, the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> in remembrance of the creation of the world: The <hi>Paſſeover</hi> in remembrance of the deliveraunce of the firſt borne: The <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> in remembrance of the lawe which was giuen: the feaſt <hi>of the ſound of trumpets,</hi> as ſome ſaie for the deliverance of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but more probably <hi>propter liberationem à ſervitute quae inter Iſraelitas fiebat,</hi> for the deliverance from that ſervitude which was vſuall among the Iſraelites, every ſeve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th yeare. the feaſt of <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> in remembrance that they lived in Tabernacles in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert: The feaſt of <hi>Propitiation</hi> for remiſſion of ſinnes. The feaſt of <hi>vnleavened bread Quod exierant de Aegypto in mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no timore &amp; celeritate,</hi> for that they came out of Aegypt in great feare &amp; haſt: not hauing leiſure to leauen the lumpe.</p>
            <p>Theſe are al called <hi>feſtivitates regulares,</hi> regular, <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria,</hi> ordinatie, <hi>conſuetae</hi> vſual, and were inſtituted and ordained by the commandement of God himſelfe. Others there were which were called <hi>voluntariae,</hi> inſtituted by the will and commaundement of the Magiſtrates vpon ſome iuſt and reaſonable cauſe: which though they had their inſtitution from the wil &amp; pleaſure of the governor, are no part of wil worſhip <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (a word much miſtaken among many) being not <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra legem Dei</hi> againſt the law of God, but <hi>ſecundum anologiam legis,</hi> according to the analogy of the law, nor brought in at the pleaſure of private fancies without al authoritie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Feſtum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicationis.</note>Such a one was the feaſt of the dedication of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called <hi>Feſtum Encoeniorum,</hi> which was conſtituted in remembrance of the reedifying of the Temple vnder Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robabel: this is mentioned, <hi>Ioan.</hi> 10. <hi>Facta ſunt Encoenia,
<pb facs="tcp:19695:8"/>
&amp; hyems erat,</hi> It was the feaſt of the Dedication, &amp; it was winter, for it was in December: and was celebrated by our Saviour.</p>
            <p>Such a one was the feaſt which was called <hi>Feſtum ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> the feaſt of lots, or <hi>Festum Mardochai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Feſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dochaei. Heſter. c. 9.</note> Mardochaeus his feaſt, when by the meanes of <hi>Heſter</hi> and <hi>Mardochaeus</hi> the Iewes were delivered from the ſlaughter of <hi>Haman,</hi> &amp; it is mentioned in the booke of <hi>Heſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such a one was the feaſt of <hi>Purification,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Feſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficationis.</note> when Iudas &amp; they that were with him purified the Temple which the Gentiles before had polluted. Which feaſt the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> cal <hi>Caſſen,</hi> of this in the 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">2. Mach. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And finally ſuch a one was <hi>Feſtumignis</hi> the feaſt of fire,<note place="margin">Feſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ignis.</note> inſtituted by the Iewes after they came from the captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Babylon, &amp; found the fire of the alter which lay hid in a pit or well 70. yeares and was turned into thicke and groſſe water, to be kindled againe, &amp; with the flame there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to conſume the ſacrifice vpon the Alter, 2. <hi>Mach.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">2. Mach 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer the Iewes did not only adde to the number of the feaſts inſtituted by Moſes, but they augmented the ſolemnitie of certaine of thoſe feaſts which Moſes appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For whereas <hi>Dies Calendarum or Neomenia</hi> the firſt day of the month or feaſt of new Moones,<note place="margin">Neomeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> was appointed only for ſacrifice vnto God, <hi>Propter beneficium gubernatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> and not mentioned in the 23. of <hi>Levit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 23.</note> where are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med al the ſolemne feſtivities: yet the Iewes out of their devotion <hi>ad augmentandum cultum divinum</hi> for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the ſervice of God did appoint that the Calends or Neomeniae ſhould bee <hi>Vacativae ab opere:</hi> not only to offer ſacrifice in, but in which they ſhould abſtaine from al ſervile labour, and ſo made it an holyday and great ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19695:9"/>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 81.</note>To this ſolemnity it was brought in Davids time: Pſ. 81 <hi>Buccinate in Neomenia tuba, inſigni die ſolennitatis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae,</hi> Blow vp the trumpet in the new moone: &amp;c. now no day was <hi>inſignis,</hi> notable, except is were free from labour: for then every other feſtiuitie had beene more famous.</p>
            <p>And it ſeemeth to haue bin thus ſolemnely vſed in <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus</hi> his time, to whom whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Shunamite woman went for her dead ſonne, her husband ſaid to her: <hi>Quam ob cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam vadis ad eum hodic,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Reg 4.</note> 
               <hi>non ſunt Calendae nec ſabbathu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4. Why doeſt thou goe vnto him, this day is neither the Cale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds nor the Sabboth; which argues that they were freed from labour, becauſe her husband inſinuated that ſhee ſhould goe vpon a day when he might bee at leaſure from his buiſines: making in that reſpect a ſimilitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Calends and Sabboth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note>And it was obſerved till the time of S. Auſtine among the Iewes, and ſo in al probability till now: for S. Auſtine by way of reproofe faith of the Iewiſh women in his time <hi>Foeminae Hebraeoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> melius nere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vel aliquid operis facere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, quam in Neomenijs ſuis impudicè ſaltarent.</hi> The Hebrew women were better ſpinne, or doe any worke, then immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly daunce in their new moones ſo that this ſeemeth to be a true rule which the Divines putt <hi>Non licebat Iudaeis diminuere feſtivitates quas Deus poſuerat, licebat tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eas augmentare.</hi> The Iewes might not leſſen thoſe feaſtes which God had appointed them, yet notwithſtanding it was lawful for them to augment them.</p>
            <p>Now for the newe Teſtament, the Legiſlator himſelfe Chriſt Ieſus inſtituted no holiday: for in his life time hee did not abrogate the lawe of Moſes, but obſerved thoſe feaſtes: neither did the Apoſtles vntil ſuch time as the law of Moſes being deade, it might be buried honeſtly: for
<pb facs="tcp:19695:9"/>
the Chriſtian religion had not ſo many ceremonies nor holidaies, neither was it convenient that it ſhould, in the cradle, as it had in the ſtrength and ful age of it: as alſo the people of Iſrael in their infancie in the deſert, though the ceremonial law were then given, yet obſerved but little till they came to the land of promiſe, neither then alſo, till that was in peace, and the people of Iſrael in the height of their glory.</p>
            <p>Nevertheles in the Apoſtles times, as appeareth in the new teſtament, the Lords day our Sunday was inſtituted in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of the reſurrection of our Saviour Chriſt: and S. Auſtine aſcribeth moſt of the greater feſtivities to the authority of the Apoſtles or general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels: <hi>ad Ianuar:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt ad Ianuar.</note> but Ambroſe vpon Luke nameth the Pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tecoſt or Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunday to haue bin obſerved by S. Paule himſelfe.<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> 
               <hi>Apud E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſios Paulus Pentecoſten celebrat, relaxat animam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pentecoſt. Pauli.</note> 
               <hi>quia fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei cernebat ardore feruentes,</hi> Paule kept the Pentecoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Epheſians, and enlarged his heart, becauſe he ſaw them fervent in the zeale of faith. It is not probable that he kept the Iewes Penticoſt among the heathen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>St. Auſtine <hi>Ser.</hi> 130. <hi>de tempore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtine Ser. 130 de Temp. Paraſceve. 1. Cor. 5.</note> notes that St. Paul did inſinuate the celebration of the Paſſion of our Saviour. 1. Cor. 5. ſaying <hi>Magiſter gentium docet propter crucem an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nua feſta conſtitui, epulemur inquit non in fermento veteri,</hi> The maiſter of the Gentiles teacheth that annual feaſtes muſt be appointed for the paſſion, and ſaith that we muſt feaſt but not in the olde leaven; and ſaith he, <hi>adijciens cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam agendae, ſolennitatis, ait quoniam paſcha noſtrum pro nobis immolatus eſt Christus,</hi> yeelding a reaſon why wee keepe a ſolemnity, becauſe our Paſſeover Chriſt hath bin offered for vs. And St. Origen who was not long from the
<pb facs="tcp:19695:10"/>
Apoſtles times, ſpeaking againſt Celſus of holidaies, ſaith <hi>Dies feſtos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen. contra Celſum.</note> 
               <hi>Dominicos, Paraſceves, &amp; Pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tecoſtes vnuſquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fidelis celebrat,</hi> Every faithful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> celebrateth, holidaies, the feaſt of the Paſſion &amp; Pentecoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note>In the times of St Auguſtine, which are within the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the pure primitiue church theſe ſolemnities were multiplied,<note place="margin">Aug. Pſ. 72. Aug. 27. tract. Super Ioan.</note> &amp; not only the feaſts of the Apoſtles celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but of many Martyres, as of St Cyprian, St. Laure<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and Sixtus the Martyr. vpon the 72. Pſal. &amp; the 27. tract <hi>ſuper. Ioan.</hi> and thus farre nothing amiſſe, til the Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der being overcharged with falſe and counterfeite popiſh ſaints, we reduced it to the compaſſe of our moſt auncient and Chriſtian feſtiuities.</p>
            <p>Al which feſtivities notwithſtanding this reformation haue found their enemies, and oppugning arguments, as alſo this daie which now we celebrate.</p>
            <p>The former haue two ſorts of adverſaries and thoſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite and in extremities, for ſome are prophane in abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating them, ſome ſuperſtitious in the obſervation of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Petrobu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiani.</note>Of the former ſort were thoſe prophane <hi>Petrobuſiani</hi> of whom we read of in St-Bernardes life, and our late Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes, who hold that theſe holidaies are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that no man hath, nor ever had, ſince Moſes auctority to inſtitute them in the old teſtament, nor in the new except the Apoſtles, who inſtituted, as they ſay, the Sunday only, and affirme moreover that al feſtival daies belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial law of Moſes, &amp; therfore ought not to be amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Chriſtians, ſeeing the ceremonies of the old law were ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled by Chriſt, and ſo conſequently abrogated: never co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that we vſe many ceremonials which were in the law of Moſes, and abrogated alſo, <hi>ſed non ex vi legis Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicae, ſed ex ratione legis,</hi> but not by the vertue or force of
<pb facs="tcp:19695:10"/>
Moſes his law, but only in regard of the reaſon therof; and many feaſts not in remembrance of the bleſſings done to the Iewes, but by Chriſt vnto Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The textes they alleadge are theſe. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.16.<note place="margin">Col. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let no man iudge you in meate or in drinke, or in the part of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyday: you obſerue daies and moneths, and yeares, I feare you leaſt I haue laboured in vaine amongſt you, Gal.</hi> 4.10.<note place="margin">Gal. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Alius iudicat inter diem &amp; diem, alius iudicat omne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diem, Rom</hi> 14.5.<note place="margin">Rom. 14.5.</note> 
               <hi>Some iudge betwixte day and day, and ſome call into iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment every day.</hi> But the firſt and the laſt are referred to the feaſts of the Iewes, &amp; the ſecond to the ſolemnities of the Gentiles, as appeareth by the natural courſe of thoſe texts and the expoſition of the fathers vpon thoſe places.</p>
            <p>But we haue for the warrant of our holydaies, firſt <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum legis Moſaicae, the example of Moſes his law,</hi> which is alleadged by them that are learned for one reaſon why our Saviour Chriſt did inſtitute none: then <hi>Rationem legis Moſaicae, the reaſon of Moſes his lawe,</hi> to wit, a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Gods bleſſings. And thirdly, the practiſe and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Chriſt his Church, ſince his comming, fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the promiſe of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.4.</note> 
               <hi>If two or three hee gathered togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my name I will be in the midſt of them,</hi> how much more if the whole congregation were aſſembled, which with an army of praiers ſhoulde enforce his mercy. And laſtly, the counſel of the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">1. Cor 4.</note> 
               <hi>Omnia decenter &amp; ordine fiant, Everything muſt be done decently and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> But what order or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecencie would be found, if everie man ſhould ſerue God at his owne pleaſure, at his owne time, after his owne manner.</p>
            <p>They who are ſuperſtitious in obſerving of holydaies are of two ſorts; for either they obſerue ſuperſtitious feaſts or obſerue the true feaſts ſuperſtitiouſly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19695:11"/>
               <note place="margin">Papiſtes.</note>Of the former ſort are the Papiſts who obſerue the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of ſo many fabulous and ridiculous Saints, whoſe Legends are the ſcoffe and ſcorne of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ebionites.</note>And alſo the old <hi>Ebionites,</hi> heretickes who taught that Chriſtians ſhould obſerue the feaſts both of the olde and new teſtament,<note place="margin">Euſeb hiſt. eccle. lib 3. cap. 27. Greg. 11. epiſt. 3.</note> both the Sabboth and the Lords daie alſo, as appeareth, <hi>Euſeb. hiſt. eccleſ. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. Which error many would haue reviued in Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> his time, as appeareth, <hi>lib.</hi> 11. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 3. and they ſaie that the Chriſtians which now liue in Ethiopia obſerue them both.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Epiphan. haer. 30. Iraen. l. 1. ca. 26.</note>Now Saint <hi>Paule</hi> doth ſo manifeſtly croſſe this opinion of the <hi>Ebionites</hi> that they therfore refuſed his writings, &amp; termed him an Apoſtata, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> teſtifieth in the ſame place, <hi>Epiphan. haer.</hi> 30. <hi>Iraen. li.</hi> 1. ca. 26.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Centuria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores.</note>And yet the Centuriatores Magdeburgenſes doe not lie, as the Ieſuits falſlie charge them, when they ſaie <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolum Paulum indifferenter obſervaſſe Sabbatha &amp; domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicum,</hi> that the Apoſtle Paule did indifferentlie obſerue both the Sabboth and the Lords day; for ſo he did a long time; for the Apoſtles are noted in the firſt times after Chriſt, <hi>Iudaizare &amp; Sabbatizare</hi> to be a Iew to a Iew, and a Chriſtian to a Gentile, to winne both.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Saint Paul obſerved the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both. Act. 13.</note>That Saint Paule obſerved the Sabboth appeareth in the 13. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> where <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> are ſaid to <hi>enter into the Sinagogue vpon the Sabboth day.</hi> In the ſame place they <hi>entreate the Gentiles that the next Sabboth they might preach to them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 16.</note> and Saint Paule <hi>diſputed three Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths at Theſſalonica. Act.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.</note>That hee likewiſe obſerued the Lordes daie, appeareth <hi>Act.</hi> 20. where it is ſaide that <hi>the brethren came togither, vno Sabbathorum, ideſt, die Dominica, ad frangendum pane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt day of the Sabboth, that is, the Lords day, to
<pb facs="tcp:19695:11"/>
breake bread: for in a fewe of the firſt yeares the Apoſtles obſerved certaine ceremonial lawes of Moſes becauſe of the weake brethren among the Iewes, as thinges indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and became Iewes to the Iewes to gaine the Iewes: but when the obſtinate Iewes and falſe brethren required the obſeruation of the lawe as neceſſary to ſalvation, they reſiſted them earneſtly, and ſtoutly defended the doctrine of the abrogation of the law; and liberty of the Goſpel: yea St. Paule reprooved St. Peter at Antioche when hee did <hi>Iudaizare</hi> in favour or feare of the falſe brethren Gal. 2.<note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> &amp; taught that the law was ſo farre abrogated, that if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were circumciſed, or obſerved other ceremonies of the law as neceſſary to ſaluation, he could not be ſaued. Gal. 5.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And this was the cauſe why the Ebionites called St. Paule an Apoſtata becauſe at the firſt he obſerved the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the law, and afterward refuſed them vtterly, and preached againſt them.</p>
            <p>They that obſerue the true feaſts ſuperſtitiouſly are ſuch as doe Iudaizare, which wil ſee their neighbour periſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they wil relieue him on the Sabboth day: ſuch was he even of this ſhire, who lately when his fathers ribbes were broken would not ride for a bone-ſetter on the Sabboth day: ſuch a one was he who in my memory went out from among vs, and preached in a market towne in this ſhire, that it was a greater ſin to doe <hi>ſervile opus in Sabbathe</hi> &amp; ſo to violate it, then to do murther or commit adultery: becauſe the commandement of keeping the Sabboth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longes to the firſt table, and murther and adultery but to the ſecond.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeake briefely to the point (for I haue far to goe and little time to ſpend.) The reaſon is of no force, but the poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be peſtelent: for the <hi>abſtaining from labour which
<pb facs="tcp:19695:12"/>
is but a ceremonie,</hi> is <hi>de iure humano,</hi> not <hi>de iure divino;</hi> and therefore the violating of this commaundement in that point is not ſo grievous a ſinne, though it pertaine to the firſt table, as murther and adultery, which is againſt Gods expreſſe law in the ſecond table.</p>
            <p>For may it pleaſe you in a worde to vnderſtand that in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of keeping the Sabboth, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what moral, and ſomewhat ceremonial.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> It is ceremonial that the Sabboth ſhould be on this or that day, and therfore it is changed to the Sunday.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The quantity of obſerving it is ceremonial, as to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from al labour, from dreſſing our meate, and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling our fire Exod. 35.<note place="margin">Exod. 35.</note> this alſo is ceaſed: we being not ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſtreightned in our feaſts as the Iewes were. 3. It is ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial that for one whole day or 24. howers wee ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> labor. 4. It is ceremonial that this ſhould once be done in every ſeaven daies. Theſe two laſt ceremonies are not changed in Chriſtianity becauſe they had no ſpecial ſignification: thoſe two former were cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, <hi>Quia vmbra erant futurorum</hi> becauſe they were figures of thinges to come, and when the truth came the figures did vaniſh.</p>
            <p>It is moral that ſome time ſhould be allowed to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, that we might reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber his benefits &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his holy name: to breake this law which is <hi>de iure diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> that is, to dedicate no time to the ſervice of God, is worſe then adultery, worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> murther, but to breake the ceremonies of it, which are <hi>de iure humano,</hi> is not ſo great a ſinne as murther or adultery which are of the ſecond ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; <hi>de iure divino,</hi> againſt the expreſſe law of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Nowe I come to the enemies of this Solemnity which now we celebrate, of which ſince a right reverend &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:19695:12"/>
brother of ours hath written very religiouſly,<note place="margin">D. Holland</note> learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and largely, I ſhal neede to ſay the leſſe; yet thus much briefely. That <hi>Reynolds, Sanders, Stapleton</hi> and the reſt of the rigide and ſalt humored Papiſts take exception eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially againſt two points in this Sole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nity: the <hi>firſt</hi> is at the <hi>Inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as if it were without auctority (for that it is now amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our ſolemnities we wil not deny:) the <hi>ſecond</hi> againſt the <hi>manner of ſolemnizing it,</hi> as though we preferred it before the feaſtes of our Sauiour Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For the former, that the magiſtrate hath had both au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctority and practiſe of inſtituting holidaies vpon extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Gods bleſſings, hath bin proved both by the examples vnder the Law, and vnder the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>That the Iewes <hi>poterant quotidie inſtituere festiuitates quaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſeruatio duraret ſingulis annis, vel fieret ſolum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abulenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>might daily inſtitute holidaies the obſervation whereof might either continue every yeare or onely be held once,</hi> is A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulenſis aſſertion. 1. <hi>Paral. cap.</hi> 16. <hi>q.</hi> 14. That they appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>annual,</hi> you haue heard before vnder <hi>Mardacheus, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemias, Iudas Machabaeus,</hi> that they augmented in cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies ſome yeare more then other the feaſts appointed in the lawe,<note place="margin">2: Eſd: 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> appeareth both in <hi>Eſdras</hi> time when the feaſt of Tabernacles was ſo royally ſolemnized that it is ſaid <hi>Non feceru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t à diebus Ioſua (filij Nun) talia filii Iſrael vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad diem illum</hi> 2. <hi>Eſà.</hi> 8. <hi>The children of Iſraell never did ſuch things, no not from the daies of Ioſhua the ſonne of Nun vnto that day</hi> and Ioſias celebrated ſuch a Paſſeover in the 18. yeare of his raigne when he had purged the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Idols,<note place="margin">4. Reg: 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Quale non fuerat actum a temporibus Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Iſraelit arum vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad Ioſiam.</hi> 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 23. <hi>as had not beene from the times of the Iudges of Iſrael vnto Ioſias.</hi> That they appointed ſuch as are called by the Civilians <hi>Repentina,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19695:13"/>
inſtituted for once vpon a ſuddeine occaſion, appeareth by David who while the Arke was in his houſe <hi>faciebat omnes dies ſolennes propter honorem Arca, ſaltem ad obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vationem ceremoniaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> made every day a ſolemne day for the honour of the arke, at the leaſt concerning the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of ceremonies. <hi>Abulenſ.</hi> and ſolemniſed the daie of his inauguration into his kingdome in this Pſal.</p>
            <p>That the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magiſtrate hath at leaſt as much au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in conſtituting newe feſtivities, and augmenting the olde, as the Iewes had, cannot with any probability be denied. They not only appointed the feaſtes which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our redemption, but the memorials of the Apoſtles, &amp; ſome holy Martyres. <hi>Constantine</hi> held a feaſt for ioy of the ſetling of the Goſpel &amp; Chriſtianity in his time:<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 1. de vita Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantini.</note> Other Emperors celebrated <hi>auſpicia lucis,</hi> the day of their birth: other <hi>Ortum imperij,</hi> the beginning of their raigne: other <hi>festiuitates repentinas</hi> ſuddeine feaſtes, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ioy for victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie over Gods enemies, the Turkes, and infidels. Al which argue ſuficient auctority, both for the inſtitution and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of this feſtivity.</p>
            <p>Which although it had his original at the firſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that of St. Paule.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> 1. Tim. 2. where he exhorteth <hi>ſupplications, praiers, thankeſgivings, interceſsions, to be made for kings, &amp; for all that are in auctority:</hi> Eſpecially ſeeing we had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to that end propoſed by the Apoſtle, namely by reaſon of her Maieſties raigne <hi>to haue liberty to leade a peaceable and quiet life in all godlines &amp; honeſty:</hi> Yet for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as ſince that time it hath bin confirmed by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and approbation of the magiſtrate, and by note in the Calender, and by ſpecial praiers appointed for it, I ſee no reaſon,<note place="margin">Caluino <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>irc. l. 2. c. 18.</note> but an high meaſure of malice only, in <hi>Reynolds</hi> in his <hi>Caluine-T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> to liken it to the encreaſe &amp; progreſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:19695:13"/>
that Idolatrie mentioned in the 14. of Wiſedome ver. 14.15.16. Where the father <hi>made an image for his dead ſon, and worſhipped it as a God, and ordained ceremonies and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafices, which grewe to a custome in proceſſe of time, &amp; was made a law;</hi> except peradventure he thinke that there is onely a progreſſe in ſinne &amp; not in virtue, as in their ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from ſlaunder to libelling: a progreſſe in Idolatry, as in their Churches from an Image to an Idol, from an Idol to al heatheniſh ceremonies &amp; ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but no progreſſe in true religion either inwardly from faith to faith, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace to grace, or outwardly from leſſe to more worſhip, from fewer to more devour and religious ceremonies, which I haue obſerved before to haue beene the courſe of Gods Church, both in the olde and new Teſtament.</p>
            <p>To conclude this pointe. If the particular Church of England had auctority in Queene Maries daies to appoint two ſolemne &amp; Anniverſarie Maſſes to be yerely celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in St. Maries, the one on the 18. of Februarie beeing the Nativity of Queene Marie, &amp; the other on the firſt of October, on which ſhe was crowned, at which Maſſes the whole Vniverſity ſhould bee preſent from the beginning to the end, and there devoutly pray <hi>for the good estate of the King and the Queene, and for the peace of this their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Realme,</hi> and moreover appointed two ſolemne proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions vpon the ſame daies being matters of greater ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity then now we vſe in theſe our meetings: I doubt not to affirme that the particular Church of England hath alſo auctority ſufficient to inſtitute, if ſo it pleaſe, the celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Nativity, and inauguration of her excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, with publike ſermons, common praiers, &amp; thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving for her godly &amp; peaceable raigne, &amp; the vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able bleſſing received by her, the choſen inſtrument of
<pb facs="tcp:19695:14"/>
God for our good.</p>
            <p>The other accuſation is againſt the <hi>manner of ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing</hi> it,<note place="margin">Saunders.</note> with ringing, and bonfires, and anthims, and ſermons, and feaſtings, not onely ſolemnely, but <hi>ſolenniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimè moſt ſolemnely,</hi> as though it were preferred before Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Chriſtmas, the bleſſed memorials of our Saviour Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But may it pleaſe you to vnderſtand that one feaſt or holiday is ſaid to be more ſolemne or greater then another for many cauſes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Becauſe wee abstaine more from worke in it, then in anie other;</hi> in this ſenſe the Sabboth among the Iews, was more ſolemne then other feaſts. Nowe foraſmuch as no man is forbidden bodilie labor this daie, which they are on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies and other great Feſtivities, therefore you ſee that in this reſpect it is inferiour to them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly one feaſt was more ſolemne then another, <hi>becauſe more ceremonies were vſed in it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in others:</hi> thus though the Sabboth were abſolutely the chiefe feaſt of the Iewes, yet in this reſpect without preiudice to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Sabboth, every feaſt among the Iews was grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the Sabboth, in as much as they had al more cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies belonging to them by the law of Moſes: to graunt then that wee had more ceremonies in the divine ſervice this day then on Chriſtmas day, doth not argue this ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie greater then it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly one feaſt was more ſolemne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, <hi>Becauſe more aſſembled togither for the celebratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the feast:</hi> thus the three feaſts of Eaſter, Whit-ſuntide, and the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, in which al the people were bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to aſcend vp to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacrifice in the Temple of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the Sabboth, and al other feaſts. Now foraſmuch
<pb facs="tcp:19695:14"/>
as no man is forced by law to this ſolemnity, and fewe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnize it but the better ſorte of the people, &amp; maſters of families, in this reſpect it is inferiour to the Sabboth &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our ſolemne feaſtes, to which al men with their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies by law are forced to reſort.</p>
            <p>Laſtly one feaſt was more ſolemne then another, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> it was celebrated with greater magnificence and iote:</hi> thus the celebration of the Paſſeover was moſt famous in the time of king <hi>Ioſias,</hi> who when he had purged the land from al Idolatry, celebrated the Paſſeover ſo magnificent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the like was not done, <hi>A diebus Iudicum qui iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt Iſrael.</hi> 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 23. <hi>from the daies of the Iudges which iudged Iſraell,</hi> and in this reſpect for the ioy and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence which is vſed in it, this day which now we celebrate is a moſt ſolemne day, like the day mentioned in my texte, the verie end of the inſtitution of it being, <hi>exultare &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari in ea,</hi> to reioice both inwardlie and outwardlie in it, which is the laſt point I intende to ſpeake of.</p>
            <p>If this then be the end of the inſtitution of this ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>laetari &amp; exultare in ea</hi> to reioice and be glad in it, that is, <hi>gaudere in domino vehementer,</hi> as S. Paule ſaith, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> to reioice in the Lord greatly <hi>gaudere in domino non in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> to reioice in the Lord, not in the gift: that is, <hi>Non prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter donum finaliter, ſedde dono materialiter, not finallie for the gift, but materially of the gift,</hi> &amp; it be done in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree: both inwardly, <hi>delectatione voluntatis in bono acquiſito</hi> in the gladnes of the minde for the good gotten in this great bleſſing which we now remember: and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, <hi>per redundationem in exultatione,</hi> that is <hi>in extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaltatione, quia ab anima in corpus ſalit, in abundance of ioy,</hi> when the delight of our ſoule doth as it were leap forth into our body, ſo that we doe every one in particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb facs="tcp:19695:15"/>
with the Prophet <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.</note> 
               <hi>Cor meum &amp; caro mea exulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt in Deum vivu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> both my hart inwardly, &amp; my fleſh outwardly haue reioiced in the living God, and that in the higheſt degree, with al readines and alacritie, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing as David did when the Arke was brought home, or to melodious muſicke as in this Pſalme in the day of his inauguration; ſeeing it is a rule, <hi>Facientes ex gaudio faciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſicut facientes exhabitu,</hi> thoſe that doe any thing in ioie doe it as if it were done by habit, and facilitie: what preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice I beſeech you is this to our moſt Chriſtian ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which are <hi>ſoleuniores</hi> in many other and greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note>Wherefore whoſoever thou be Prieſt or Ieſuite which ſaieſt in thy hart, <hi>Quie ſcere faciamus festivitates eorum à terra,</hi> as the wickedman in the Pſalme, let vs take away their feaſts and ſolemnities, from the face of the earth, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by our treaſon on her Maieſties perſon, or invaſion of her country, or by libels and vndermining ſophiſmes, take heede what you doe, <hi>Non eſt iocandum cum dijs, It is ill ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting with Gods,</hi> Princes are the Gods of the earth, Gods immediate lieuetenants, to whom hee hath imparted his name, and vouchſafed them a great parte of his externall worſhip it is ill ieſting with them: to ſcoffe, or to raile at them, to libell againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or their ſubiects, either for their <hi>allegeance,</hi> or <hi>religious dueties</hi> to God in their behalfe, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that notable rule in the law of God,<note place="margin">Exod. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Principi populi non maledices, thou ſhalte not revile the prince of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> He that curſeth his Father or Mother, much more hee that curſeth the father of his cuntry, the Crowes of the vallies will plucke out his eies, his fleſh ſhall be foode for the fowles of the aire: God himſelfe who hath placed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his ſeat to governe the earth and the provinces of it, wil
<pb facs="tcp:19695:15"/>
defende them with many guardes, even as the apple of an eie is defended: it is not flying into forraine countries that can deliver you from your alleagiance, or from puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due for the violating of it. <hi>Coelum non hominem mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant qui trans mare currunt,</hi> you may flie beyond the ſeas from the natural aire of your natiue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, but not from your ſelues, nor your natural alleagiance, no (as I may ſay) from that natural, or rather ſupernatural ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance which attendeth on you: for God either putteth a hooke in your noſtrels and brings you backe againe the ſame way you went to ſuffer condigne puniſhment for theſe lewde and moſt vnchriſtian practiſes; or you periſh miſerably like runagates and vagabonds, or exiled malefactours in a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine countrey.</p>
            <p>But to paſſe over this ſort of malitious cavillers (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I hope and verily thinke that not any one ill affected doth heare me this day, howſoever we be ſlandred by our mothers children, that we ſwarme with Papiſts, that wee fall away dayly in great multitudes, that our chiefe divines whom ſome note vnder the name of <hi>Formaliſts,</hi> are ready to ioine both heart and hand with them, to the incredible incouragement of all ſortes of Romaniſtes, and to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of her Maieſties government, the diſcredit of this Chriſtian ſocietie, the diſparagement of their own iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and diſcretion, who wound to the heart that religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they pretend to defend: of which vpon farther occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſurely we will hereafter haue further diſcourſe. To paſſe ouer this &amp; come to our ſelues, let vs embrace as wee haue begun the example of this people in the inauguration of king David, and this good counſel of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Deum timete, Regem honorate,</hi> feare God, and honor the king; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor him in thy heart, honor him with thy handes and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb facs="tcp:19695:16"/>
honor him with thy tongue: practiſe no diſloialtie, ſpeake no diſloialty, thinke no diſloialty, no not in thy leaſt thought, in thy ſecret chamber; for beſides that the fowles of the aire will bewraie it, and the clowdes of thy diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented countenance diſcover it, as I told you of late, there is ever a progreſſe in ſinne, it neuer ſtands ſtil, it ſtands not at one ſtay, but paſſeth ſecretly from evill thoughts to ill wordes, and from ill words to fowle actions, and then it is ripe and calleth for his puniſhment.</p>
            <p>And ſurelie God is verie iealous of the honour of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and leaſt we ſhould in anie ſorte deſpiſe them and bee diſobedient vnto them, becauſe wee be all made of one mould of the earth, as the daies of the yeare of one ſunne in the firmament, and therefore are all <hi>pares in eſſe naturae</hi> equall one to another in nature, that there might be a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference <hi>in eſſe merali</hi> in civile being, God honoreth Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with his owne name, ſo that they are called <hi>Gods,</hi> and <hi>Gods annointed,</hi> and the <hi>ſonnes of the moſt high:</hi> he calleth them by his owne name, and furniſheth them with divine and ſupernatural qualities.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Prov: 16:</note>For there is <hi>divinatio in labijs regis,</hi> divination in the lips of the king, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. ſo that they do often foreſee, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeake,<note place="margin">1: Sam. 10:</note> and foretell things to come, and it is noted in the firſt kings that ever God inſtituted: for as ſoone as <hi>Samuell</hi> powred the viol of oile vpon <hi>Saule</hi> he was changed into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother man, and the ſpirit of God falling vpon him hee did prophecie among the Prophets: and as ſoone as <hi>David</hi> was annointed by <hi>Samuell</hi> the ſcripture ſaith, <hi>Directus eſt ſpiritus domini in David à die illa &amp; deinceps,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam: 16:</note> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. <hi>The ſpirite of the Lorde came vpon David from that daie forwardes:</hi> and when <hi>Caiphas</hi> who was the high Prieſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Conſiſtorie ſaide, <hi>Expedit quod vnus moriatur
<pb facs="tcp:19695:16"/>
pro populo,</hi> It is expedient that one ſhould die for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he ſaid not that of himſelfe, ſaith the text, <hi>ſed cum erat po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifex ill us anni prophetavit,</hi> but in that he was the high Prieſt that yeare he did prophecie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is a certaine <hi>depth in the hart of a king.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Prov. 25.</note> 
               <hi>VVhich none can ſeeke out, even higher then the heaven, &amp; deeper then the earth.</hi> Prov. 25.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they haue gifts of healing incureable diſeaſes,<note place="margin">3</note> which are miraculous and aboue nature, ſo that when <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſian</hi> was ſeene to performe ſuch a cure, the people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded he ſhould be Emperour as <hi>Tacitus</hi> notes.<note place="margin">Tacitus.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4</note> they haue power abſolute without limitation accountable only to God for their actions.</p>
            <p>Fifthly they haue authoritie to bleſſe their dutifull and loyall ſubiects, and they are bleſſed:<note place="margin">5</note> &amp; authoritie to curſe their ſubiects diſobedient, &amp; they are curſed with tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral curſe, as I could prooue both by reaſon and examples out of the ſcriptures if the time would permit.</p>
            <p>And as God is iealous of their honour, ſo much more of their ſafeties, and therefore he ſets a <hi>guarde of Angels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them. He keepeth them as the apple of his eie;</hi> Pſal. 17. <hi>He hides them vnder the ſhaddow of his wings:</hi> he will not haue them touched, <hi>Touch not my annointed, Pſalm.</hi> 105. Everie touch with hart, with hand, with tongue, is treaſon <hi>laeſa maiestas,</hi> the maieſtie of the Prince is wounded by it, and therfore <hi>David</hi> was ſorrie at the hart when he cut but the lap of <hi>Saules</hi> garment. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.6.</p>
            <p>Finally he revengeth their wrongs before his own; trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before blaſphemies againſt himſelfe <hi>prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bonum vniverſi</hi> for the good of mankind; and more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely then his owne with temporal puniſhment.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould inſtaunce in theſe giftes and graces where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal
<pb facs="tcp:19695:17"/>
God hath plentifully endowed her excellent maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and ſtand to amplifie the wonderful depth of the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of her hart, evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to her Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel in her moſt weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affaires, to her ſubiects generally in her divine ſpeaches at every parliament, to vs in particular in her excellent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations beyond admiration and imitation: or this gifte of prophecie, as I may call it, whereby ſhee hath foreſeene, foretold, and, if I may ſo ſaie, foreſpoken that which an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie wiſdome could not imagine: or her manifold bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings on well deſerving ſubiectes, confirmed as it may ſeeme, by God to them and their poſterity, if they walke in loialtie and true obedience: or the ſupernatural cures of weake diſeaſed people, amounting to the number of three or foure hundred a yeare: or the divine provide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God in defending her as the apple of his eie, from ſo many trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, conſpiracies, rebellions at home &amp; abroade; it might be thought by ſome of the maligners of this feſtivity, that I ſtand more vpon the praiſes of my earthly miſtres, then vpon the honor and glory of my heavenly Lorde and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>Wherfore leaving theſe things to your particular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, let vs conclude with that other part of St. Paules cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel, with honoring praiſing &amp; magnifying God the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and preſerver of this great bleſſing: &amp; becauſe no ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony was ever more acceptable to him then oblation and ſacrifice, and <hi>ſacrificia legalia</hi> ſacrifices of the Lawe be abrogated, let vs offer to him our ſpiritual ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>Firſt our almes, the workes of mercie &amp; charity, which is the oblation of our temporal ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; &amp; St. Paule calles it <hi>Hoſtiam acceptam &amp; placentem Deo, a ſacrifice accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pleaſing vnto God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Secondly the humbling and mortifying of our bodies,
<pb facs="tcp:19695:17"/>
which is the oblation of our corporal ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> &amp; St. Paul calles it. Rom. 12. <hi>Hoſtiam vinentem, ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctam, Deo placen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, a living ſacrifice holy and pleaſing vnto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly our devotions in praiſing and magnifying God for this admirable bleſſing; which is the oblation of our ſpiritual ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> and St. Paule calles it Heb. 13 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>ſacrifice of praiſe,</hi> and interpretes it, <hi>the fruit of their lippes which confeſse his name:</hi> and <hi>Oſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oſe:</note> 
               <hi>the calues of our lippes,</hi> and our Prophet, Pſal. 26, <hi>Hoſtiam vociferatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> and <hi>Lyra, hostiam iubilationis,</hi> that is, the ſacrifice of thankeſgiving and ioy.</p>
            <p>To conclude, as her excellent Maieſtie with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet David in this Pſal. cries out in remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Gods benefites in his miraculous preſerving her ſo many yeares from ſo many dangers, <hi>Non moriar ſed viuam</hi> I ſhal not die but liue, <hi>vt narre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opera domini,</hi> that I may declare the workes of the Lord.</p>
            <p>As we with the Prieſtes in this Pſalme doe <hi>benedicere populo ex domo dei,</hi> bleſſe <hi>the people of</hi> the houſe of God, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating his benignity ſaying, <hi>Deus dominus, &amp; illuxit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, God is our Lord, and hath as this day illightened vs</hi> with the light of the Goſpel, and as it is in the olde tranſlation, doe <hi>conſtituere diem ſolennem in condenſis,</hi> ſo that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God come togither in <hi>denſitate plebis,</hi> as <hi>Lyra</hi> cals it, in great abundance, and <hi>vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad cernua altaris,</hi> ſo that the Church is filled even to the doores.</p>
            <p>So let al good ſubiects ioyne with this people in cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating this day, and ſing <hi>Haec eſt dies quam fecit dominus, exultemus &amp; latemur in ea, This is the day which the Lord hath made let vs reioyce and be glad therein. O domine da ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem, O domine da proſperitatem,</hi> O Lord ſend her ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, O Lord ſend her proſperity: <hi>Non moriatur ſed vivat,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19695:18"/>
let her not die but liue, that ſhee may declare thy wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous workes to many generations: that wee ſolemnizing many of theſe daies to the glory of thy name, and comfort and ioy of our owne harts, may after this triumphing, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vmph and reioyce with thee in body and ſoule in thy ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting kingdome: through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the Father and the holy Ghoſt be all power honour and glory both now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19695:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
